  <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Certification Goals</title>
    <simpara>
      The following goals drive the certification effort and therefore 
      encapsulate the core of the measurement requirements for the 
      project. 
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      The project itself is considered a demonstration vehicle and initial 
      product to move forward. As such, the software is not considered 
      mission critical or sensitive to failures. It should, however, be 
      adequately reliable for use in small scale industrial applications, 
      meaning that failures, if they occur at all, should be immediate and 
      obvious. 
    </simpara>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          The system should be semantically complete, and testing of all 
          primitives and language features should succeed to a reasonable 
          metric. No feature should be unimplemented to at least a basic 
          degree.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          Testing need not cover performance metrics, though testing and 
          verification of optimizations should be conducted.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          System should test every requirement.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          Testing should cover both compilation and execution of compiled 
          code, and should cover both error conditions in compilation as 
          well as error conditions in the executed code. 
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          Certify the correctness and reliability of the compiled code to 
          99% reliability at 95% confidence. 
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          Certify the reliability of executing the compiler to 90% at 95% 
          confidence.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          There should be no known faults in the generated code.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
