  <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Statistical Measures of Software Quality</title>
    <simpara>
      Two primary metrics will be used to certify software quality, the 
      Mean Time To Failure and Reliability. The MTTF and Reliability will 
      be calculated per increment on the basis of whole system sampling 
      using the sampling model for statistical benchmarks. Both will be 
      expressed in terms of individual test case executions, as opposed to 
      some metric of time. 
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      The MTTF and Reliability are connected to one another, with the 
      MTTF expressed in terms of reliability by the following expression:
    </simpara>
    <programlisting>÷1-Reliability</programlisting>
    <simpara>
      We will use a zero-failures metric for certification. This means 
      that an increment will be certified only after it has been 
      shown to have zero failures in a statistically representative 
      testing session. The method for calculating the statistical 
      significance is the sampling method, which has the benefits of being 
      a conservatice measure that is simple to calculate. Given a desired 
      reliability and confidence, we can determine the number of test 
      cases that must run without failure using the following calculation:
    </simpara>
    <programlisting>⌈(10⍟1-C)÷10⍟R</programlisting>
    <simpara>
      Here, <varname>C</varname> is the desired confidence and 
      <varname>R</varname> is the desired reliability. 
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      In our requirements, we have two different reliability metrics, 
      since we separate compiler reliability into the reliability of the 
      generated code and the reliability of the compiler itself. The 
      following table gives the number of test cases with zero failures 
      that must run in order to certify a version of the compiler 
      component at the desired reliability and confidence, as determined 
      by the certification goals listed above.
    </simpara>
    <informaltable frame="void" rules="rows">
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Component</th>
          <th>Reliability</th>
          <th>Confidence</th>
          <th>Test Cases</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Compiler</td>
          <td>0.90</td>
          <td>0.95</td>
          <td>29</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Generated Code</td>
          <td>0.99</td>
          <td>0.95</td>
          <td>299</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
