<glosslist xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Tasks</title>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 1</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Create the <citetitle>Cleanroom Engineering Guide</citetitle></title>
        <para>
          Use the 
          <citetitle>Cleanroom Software Engineering Reference Model</citetitle>
          as the basis for defining or revising the project's 
          <citetitle>Cleanroom Engineering Guide</citetitle>, including:
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Project-specific tailoring and refinement of the Cleanroom 
            processes. Define and document clear process implementation 
            guidance for the Cleanroom project.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Identification and documentation of facilities, hardware 
            and software environments, and tools to support Cleanroom 
            processes, with guidelines for their use.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 2</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Create the <citetitle>Software Development Plan</citetitle></title>
        <para>
          Use the <citetitle>Statement of Work</citetitle> and/or 
          <citetitle>Software Requirements</citetitle> to define or revise the 
          <citetitle>Software Development Plan</citetitle>, including the 
          following plans:
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Project Mission Plan</citetitle>: Define the overall 
            mission, goals, and objectives of the software product and 
            the Cleanroom development project.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Project Organization Plan</citetitle>: Define the 
            structure, responsibilities, and relationships of the Cleanroom 
            project organization. Identify points of contact in customer 
            and peer organizations.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Work Product Plan</citetitle>: Define the Cleanroom work 
            products and customer deliverables to be produced during the 
            project.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Schedule and Resource Plan</citetitle>: Define 
            estimates for overall schedules, milestones, and budgets. Define 
            staffing, system, and other resource requirements. These 
            estimates will be refined in the Increment Planning Process.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Measurement Plan</citetitle>: Define product and process 
            measures for managing the project, including goals for Cleanroom 
            software certification and standards for statistical process 
            control. Define the use of measures in project reviews and decision 
            making.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Reuse Analysis Plan</citetitle>: Define methods for 
            identifying and evaluating opportunities to reuse existing 
            assets and create new, reusable assets. Reusable assets include 
            domain models, reference architectures, software specifications, 
            designs, implementations, and usage models. Define specific 
            opportunities for reuse.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Risk Analysis Plan</citetitle>: Define methods for 
            identifying and managing risks throughout the project. 
            Define specific management and tehcnical risks associated with 
            the project.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Standards Plan</citetitle>: Identify and define 
            the application of external standards that will be used in the 
            project.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Training Plan</citetitle>: Identify project training 
            requirements, including training in the application domain, 
            development environments, and Cleanroom technology and processes. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <citetitle>Configuration Management Plan</citetitle>: Identify 
            the work prodcuts to be maintained under configuration control. 
            Define procedures for change management and configuration control 
            of work products.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glosslist>
