<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <author>Aaron W. Hsu</author>
    <date>Saturday, July 20th, 2013</date>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Engineering Change Log</title>
    <simpara>
      This document records and tracks all proposed engineering changes that 
      occur during development. An engineering change is a change proposed 
      or identified as desirable during one process that affects other work 
      products not part of the delivery of the current process. This document 
      tracks these proposed changes, their evaluation, analysis, and the 
      eventual resolution of these changes. 
    </simpara>
    <table frame="void" rules="rows">
      <title>Summary of Changes</title>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>ID</th>
          <th colspan="2">Date</th>
          <th colspan="5">Summary</th>
          <th colspan="2">Resolution</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>1</td>
          <td colspan="2">2013-07-21</td>
          <td colspan="5">Update <function>Obj</function> and <function>Fix</function> Requirements</td>
          <td colspan="2">Applied</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2</td>
          <td colspan="2">2013-07-23</td>
          <td colspan="5">Update class of valid input programs</td>
          <td colspan="2">Applied</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>3</td>
          <td colspan="2">2013-07-23</td>
          <td colspan="5">Add Dyalog Reference to Reuse Analysis</td>
          <td colspan="2">Applied</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>4</td>
          <td colspan="2">2013-07-29</td>
          <td colspan="5">Clarify exported bindings</td>
          <td colspan="2">Pending</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <orderedlist>
      <title>Change Description and Analysis</title>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Description</title>
          <para>
            During Functional Specification, the <function>Obj</function> and <function>Fix</function>
            functions were discovered to have a number of missing or undesirable requirement 
            implications. The following changes are suggested:
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              Amend Requirement 16 to require only implementing the monadic interface of 
              the <function>⎕FIX</function> function.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              An additional requirement should state that the <function>Obj</function> function 
              will produce a shared object in the given file name that has the same semantics 
              and function bindings as defined in the namespace.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              Requirements should be added to clarify the error reporting in the case of files 
              that already exist when handling <function>Obj</function> output.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Analysis</title>
          <para>
            The above requirements do not change the semantics of the requirements, 
            and only refine them. They meet the intention of the project and should 
            be implemented. 
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Description</title>
          <para>
            Functional specification revealed a possible ambiguity in the description of 
            requirement 21. Recommend the following:
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              That requirement 21 be changed to clearly indicate that only fully 
              closed namespaces are accepted; that is, only accept namespaces with 
              no free variable references.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              Additionally, a new requirement 
              prohibiting the use of the <literal>⌶</literal>-beam should be included.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A new requirement prohibiting the use of the <function>⍎</function>
              function should be added. 
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              Requirement 4 should be amended to specify D-fns, rather than Co-Dfns 
              programs.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              The new additions to the D-fns languages introduced by Co-Dfns should 
              be added and fully defined.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              It should be remarked that no assignment which changes the overall 
              nameclass of a variable is allowed. 
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A requirement detailing the unsupported operators should be added. 
              These operators include the <function>&amp;</function> operator as well as 
              the <function>⍠</function> operator.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Analysis</title>
          <para>
            No semantic change is introduced based on the intention of the design, and 
            are at an early enough stage so as to not affect more than the functional 
            specification, so this should be implemented.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Description</title>
          <para>
            The primary specification for the D-fns language appears in the Dyalog
            <citetitle>Programmer's Guide and Language Reference</citetitle>. This 
            should be explicitly marked as the reference document for the semantics of 
            the D-fns language.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Analysis</title>
          <para>
            This clarifies a number of implied assumptions on the part of the specifications 
            and development plans, and should be included.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Description</title>
          <para>
            Clarify the exported functions that are produced by the compiler in the exported 
            namespace to indicate that currently, only global array variables and 
            functions will be exported. Operators and other such things will not. This 
            should be entered into the requirements document.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Analysis</title>
          <para>
            This is a semantic change from the existing requirements, but does not affect 
            anything more than the functional specification, which has been amended to 
            include these adjustments anyways. Additionally, it does not add any 
            complexity, but simplifies the technical implemenation burden. The only visible 
            change to the user is the removal of operators from the public interface, which 
            is acceptable. 
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</article>