<glosslist xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Tasks</title>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 1</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Partition software functions into a series of 
        increments for development and certification</title>
        <para>
          Define the functional content of a series of software 
          increments that implement user function, execute in the system 
          environment, and accumulate into the final system.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        Use the <citetitle>Software Requirements</citetitle>
        to identify software requirements or system engineering factors that 
        may influence the definition of increment content.
      </para>
      <para>
        Use the <citetitle>Function Specification</citetitle> and the
        <citetitle>Software Architecture</citetitle> to identify required 
        software functions and their dependent relationships as a basis 
        for defining increment content.
      </para>
      <para>
        Use the <citetitle>Reuse Analysis Plan</citetitle> to identify reused
        components and allocate them to appropriate increments.
      </para>
      <para>
        Use the <citetitle>Risk Analysis Plan</citetitle>
        to identify risks that influence increment content. 
        Plan increment content to avoid or manage risks,
        with emphasis on addressing risks early in the project.
      </para>
      <para>
        Use the <citetitle>Usage Specification</citetitle> to define 
        increment content in consideration of usage probabilities; 
        specifically, to incorporate functions with high usage probabilities into 
        early increments.
      </para>
      <para>
        Identify special components, such as complex algorithms 
        requiring extensive analysis, for independent development 
        and certification prior to incorporation into the accumulating 
        increments. These components can be incorporated as reusable 
        assets in the overall increment plan.
      </para>
      <para>
        Document the required functional content of the increments in the 
        <citetitle>Increment Construction Plan</citetitle>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 2</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Refine the <citetitle>Schedule and Resource Plan</citetitle>
        by allocating schedules and resources to incremental development 
        and certification</title>
        <para>
          Within the overall constraints of the 
          <citetitle>Schedule and Resource Plan</citetitle>, allocate 
          development and certification schedules and resources
          for each increment.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        Provide for overlapping or parallel development of increments as 
        necessary to meet schedules based on the availability of 
        development resources.
      </para>
      <para>
        Define schedule points for measurement of software quality and 
        process control, and for customer evaluation of increments.
      </para>
      <para>
        Document schedule and resource allocations in the 
        <citetitle>Increment Construction Plan</citetitle> work product.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glosslist>
