  <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Software Strategy</title>
    <simpara>
      Following the NanoPass style, we divide the compiler problem
      into a series of functional, independent passes that have a
      defined input and output grammar. There are five different types
      of passes.
    </simpara>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Types of Passes</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry</term>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>A pass that is taking in data and transforming it into the AST</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Exit</term>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>A pass that is taking an AST and transforming it
          into some sort of external data</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Verification</term>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            A pass that does not alter the contents of the AST and
            just passes it along, but that might potentially signal an
            error if some invariant is broken along the way. These
            passes are used to check properties and ensure the correct
            operation of the compiler.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Standard</term>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Normal passes take an AST and return a modified AST based
            on whatever intended function defines the pass.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Optimization</term>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            And optimization pass is a pass that does not change the
            invariants on the AST, like what might happen with a
            normal pass, but instead returns something of the same
            AST, but with some sort of optimization or other
            transformation that does not affect the grammar or AST
            invariants.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <simpara>
      In the design of the system, because we are aiming as much as
      possible for aggregation, there are a few notes of
      design. Firstly, we will keep all of the functions at the
      top-level if possible, and avoid over-nesting of
      elements. Additionally, we will try to aim for simple, concise
      expressions of the solution, and avoid explicit iteration or
      recursion where possible. We should avoid the use of branching
      and conditionals where possible as well to simplify the code
      flow.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      The ASTs will be encoded into the <function>⎕XML</function>
      format for easy use. In these cases, there are a few things that
      are easy to get to in bulk, such as a single column with some
      content or the like. Thus, we should try to make certain bulk
      queries easy in the design of the ASTs, so that while things may
      be different in one access, if they share some similar aspect,
      they are easily identified as a class without excessive
      computation.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      We should avoid unnecessary complication in the AST if it is
      possible. Thus, if some information is local to a given pass and
      it is possible to keep it that way, we should avoid storing that
      information in the AST, but rather, keep it in local
      information.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      A single AST definition should be sufficient to describe the
      entire compiler languages. The input and output invariants of a
      given pass can be defined in terms of invariants on this single
      AST definition.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
      We should clearly identify the intended function and the
      properties of each pass in a manner that allows for verification
      during the clear-box design.
    </simpara>
  </section>
