<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Ancient Language, Modern Compiler</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>Aaron W. Hsu</personname>
        <affiliation><orgname>Indiana University</orgname></affiliation>
        <email>awhsu@indiana.edu</email>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <date>Thursday, March 13th, 2014</date>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        APL started it all; a venerable and infamous language,
        APL enabled the domain expert and non-programmer to
        solve problems quickly and manipulate data more productively
        than the languages of the day. To this day, however, languages
        like R, Matlab, and modern APL do not have compilers, and
        users suffer from the lack of interpreter scalability.
        Modern architectures present new challenges for aging array platforms
        and new opportunities for compilation and performance gains.
        By combining innovations in the APL language with a modular,
        memory-centric compiler design, the Co-dfns compiler delivers
        a modern compiler and development platform that enables
        existing users of APL to quickly benefit from compilation, while
        scaling  to handle large scale, general-purpose APL
        applications. The compiler design allows for high-level optimization
        of programs to target the GPU and multi-core systems without
        requiring performance tuning at lower-levels of abstraction.
        It also targets irregular algorithms, such as graph traversals,
        encouraging the broader use of high-level languages in areas
        traditionally dominated by very hand-tuned C/C++.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      General purpose array languages, such as Matlab and Dyalog APL
      excel at delivering a productive environment for domain experts to
      solve problems rapidly and with a high degree of precision. Focusing
      specifically on the APL language, a number of language features
      support the domain expert:
    </para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          APL is a mathematical style notation which maps well to
          mathematical formulae
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          APL provides a rapid feedback cycle with good integration of
          visualization and data exploration
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          APL enables a very concise representation of complex
          computation without complicated control flow or data types.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          APL supports useful abstractions such as higher-order programming
          and first-class indexing of arrays, which support rich views of
          data and manipulations of that data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      Increasingly large data sets and the advancements of modern hardware
      have brought to light a glaring weakness in existing array programming
      platforms such as Dyalog APL: they fail to scale well to massively parallel
      systems or for very high-performance numeric computations. To be sure,
      compared to many modern programming environments, APL performs remarkably
      well. However, the limitations of existing commercial and industrial strength
      APL systems prevents the sort of scaling now desirable with ready access
      to GPUs and distributed systems. Much of this scalability comes from the
      interpreted nature of the existing industrial APL implementations.
    </para>
    <para>
      Interpretation traditionally delivered important benefits to the APL language,
      including a degree of interactivity that did not exist in batch-compiled
      systems. Modern compilers, however, can compile quickly and online in such
      a way that the same interactivity gains exist, without the corresponding
      performance costs. Worse, interpretation makes it difficult to ensure certain
      constraints on execution required for good performance on modern systems,
      including memory management and locality.
    </para>
    <para>
      Traditionally, even the APL language presented challenges to compilation, with
      things like dynamic scope making useful compiler analysis difficult, at best,
      and a non-starter at worse. Thanks to work by John Scholes and others, this
      problem is disappearing rapidly; a new breed of APL is emerging as an alternative
      to traditional APL that greatly improves the compilation story.
    </para>
    <para>
      Existing efforts to design compilers for array languages sail frustratingly
      close to the conservative coastline of small, embedded languages, or else they
      deliver a language vastly different than the languages used by experts in the field.
      They often emphasize a limitation of features to improve compiler performance on
      one or more hardware platforms, an unacceptable trade-off for general-purpose
      array programming systems such as Dyalog APL.
      This presents an opportunity to pursue a new compiler that leverages modern
      advancements in compiler modularity, and targeting the specific challenges and
      platforms that seem to deliver the most promise for array languages and scaling
      their performance.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Co-dfns compiler strives to deliver an easy to use, modular, and scalable platform
      for compiling array languages. It specifically targets the dfns language subset of
      Dyalog APL extended with primitives to enable an implicit, predictable task parallelism
      that provides determinism without complicated control constructs that would otherwise
      make the system inaccessible to domain experts. It relies on the LLVM system for traditional
      compiler optimizations and instead emphasizes higher-level optimizations
      centering around memory layout and locality. It currently targets GPUs and multi-core CPUs
      with an eye towards distributed computing platforms.
    </para>
    <para>
      The current version of the compiler leverages features of the Co-dfns language to enable
      three optimizations designed as first steps towards more scalable performance in array
      languages, in particular, the array mutation and assignment semantics and a stack
      discipline on function definitions and scopes obviates the need for garbage collection,
      enabling careful memory managment directly at compile time. This stack discipline also
      allows for the implementation of nested, higher-order functions without the need for
      allocating closures, which permits a one to one mapping of co-dfns functions and llvm
      functions. This has a number of positive benefits in terms of usability and performance.
      Finally, because of the nature of the APL expression language, scalar function fusion
      promotes better cache behavior in the system and tackles one of the major
      sources of performance bottlenecks found during testing of the Dyalog APL system.
      These give a taste of the sort of optimizations the Co-dfns compiler emphasizes, with
      more planned.
    </para>
    <para>
      The compiler uses various runtime implementations of the primitives to target either
      CPU or GPU execution of the primitives. Further development plans aim to integrate these behaviors
      into the compiler itself and reduce the amount of dependence on runtime implementation
      of features for different targets.
    </para>
    <para>
      The architecture of the compiler itself <quote>eats its own dogfood</quote>; that is, the
      compiler is written in Co-dfns, using the Dyalog APL interpreter to bootstrap the system. It
      integrates into the existing Dyalog APL infrastructure so that existing users can make direct
      use of the JITed namespace directly, without requiring a separate load step. The compiler
      produces standard object files that the clang compiler system can link against any existing
      C or C++ codebase, and the compiler itself uses a nanopass design that allows for external
      systems to integrate with the compiler easily. The AST serializes as XML, allowing for
      other external tools to work on the structure. The compiler and the compiled objects intentionally
      provide easy means to embed all or part of the system into other software stacks.
    </para>
    <para>
      To judge the success of the Co-dfns compiler, three major benchmarks exist: the compiler itself,
      the Graph500 benchmark, and a set of industry supplied functions. The latter forms a real life
      set of applications upon which to test the compiler based on the people likely to use the system.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Background</title>
    <para>
      The Co-dfns compiler intentionally leverages a number of existing 
      research and practice, choosing instead to focus on the specifics 
      of array language compilation, rather than unnecessarily reinventing
      concepts that already have well established execution. These 
      include the existing APL language (in the form of dfns), existing 
      work in functional, deterministic parallelism, and low-level 
      compiler technology, in the form of LLVM.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>APL and dfns</title>
      <para>
        Kenneth Iverson birthed APL in the classroom and blackboards of 
        University mathematics, attempting to create a notation for the 
        expression of algorithms and mathematics that avoided traditional 
        faults in ambiguous and specialized notations used at the time. 
        Eventually, its executability and brevity of expression deliverd 
        impressive productivity benefits to certain expert users, who 
        were not necessarily computer scientists. However, the original 
        design of APL implementations invested heavily in interactive 
        programming, at the cost of easy compilation. 
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      The syntax of APL, in and of itself, represents a delightfully simple 
      and easy setup. Expressions have a single order of evaluation, and 
      there is very little lexical syntax. Most of the <quote>syntax</quote>
      of an APL program comes in the form of its rich base of primitives, 
      and the patterns (called idioms) that arise through increased 
      practice and familiarity with APL. However, APL's environment model, 
      including its scoping, focused heavily on dynamic code. This meant that
      the systems were usually dynamically scoped, and programs had very 
      little nesting. Structured programming was not a thing at the time, either, 
      so the GOTO statment, together with an Execute primitive (for 
      evaluating strings as code) and various other tricks represented the 
      core of APL control flow. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The dynamic nature of APL systems, at the time, presented enormous
      challenges to APL compilers. Indeed, no existing commercial compilers 
      for APL in its original form exist today. And no compiler exists today 
      which supports the full range of traditional APL control constructs, 
      such as the Execute function or GOTO. All existing research compilers 
      chose to compile only a limited subset of functionality. These research 
      compilers did, however, establish a clear feasbility of compiling APL 
      programs in a meaningful way, and some of these compilers still receive 
      active maintenance. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Like most languages, however, APL did not remain stagnant. New features 
      and capabilities continued to evolve, including structured programming 
      and object oriented programming. These new features enabled a programmer 
      to write a greater range of programs that a compiler could handle. 
      Unfortunately, many of these extensions violated the original design 
      philosophy of APL, and instead attempted to combine APL with traditional 
      programming notation. While successful, these constructs do not present 
      an attractive option for a modern compiler, in part because they only 
      address specific issues with APL compilation, and do not present a more 
      cohesive vision of APL as a modern language amenable to compilation at 
      scale. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Fortunately, John Scholes invented a new lexical syntax (called dfns) 
      for the definition of functions, branching, and error trapping. This
      new syntax overcomes many of the challenges for a new APL compiler. 
      The syntax eliminates the need for GOTO statements or execute functions 
      to perform control flow, and ensures that all variables have clear, 
      well defined, lexical scopes. See Figure YYY for a summary of this 
      syntax. Importantly, this elimination of dynamic scoping enables the 
      parser of the compiler to more accurately parse potentially ambiguous 
      expressions, whose parse tree depends on the type of specific variables. 
      The dfns syntax comes fully supported with the Dyalog APL system.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>LLVM Backend Compiler</title>
      <para>
        The LLvM project delivers an easy to use, accessible, and generic 
        low-level infrastruture for compiler development. The system has a 
        number of key features that make it attractive for use as a Co-dfns 
        compiler backend. The LLVM project contains a well documented IR 
        language that maps well to Co-dfns, supporting tail call optimization, 
        and various forms of specific optimization features at a high level, 
        such as calling conventions. A well designed C API for constructing the IR 
        and producing objects exists. The API especially lends itself to binding 
        by other language environments, such as the Dyalog APL interpreter. 
        LLVM also produces standard, C compatible objects, making integration 
        with external systems easier. Finally, it supports both standard CPU targets 
        as well as GPU targets, allowing the Co-dfns compiler to target GPUs and 
        CPUs using the same backend and IR. It also has support for JIT compilation, 
        which makes it good for doing interactive programming, of the sort 
        familiar to APL programmers. 
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Functional, deterministic parallelism</title>
      <para>
        Traditional concurrent programming often involves complicated 
        and error prone data structures or programming constructs that 
        require careful thought and knowledge to use. These simply don't 
        make parallel programming accessible to non-computer scientists, 
        which many APL programmers are. Deterministic parallelism offers 
        parallel programming benefits, but delivers predictable results, 
        such as guaranteeing that race conditions will not exist if the 
        program runs to completion, or that every run of the program 
        will produce the same result. These approaches to parallelism 
        seem much better suited for use by domain experts than traditional 
        concurrent programming constructs. Moreover, functional approaches 
        to determinstic parallelism fit neatly into the very functionally 
        oriented approach taken by dfns. A classic example is the IVar and 
        the future. An IVar is a variable that can be assigned a value 
        only once, and which blocks on reading, so that a thread cannot 
        continue computation until a value is written into the IVar that 
        it tries to read. Futures spawn a new computation in parallel to 
        an existing one, returning an Future, which is basically an IVar which 
        will eventually contain the results of the spawned function, provided 
        that the function returns. IVars and Futures are examples of 
        monotonic data structures. Monotonic data structures often support 
        the key pieces of deterministic parallel programming environments, 
        giving a much needed predictability that enables the determinism 
        guarantees. 
      </para>
    </formalpara>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Language Innovations</title>
    <para>
      The dfns language tells a fine story for spiritually functional
      data parallel programming; the bulk simd parallelism of
      APL forms the language foundation, not a veneer over mostly 
      serial programs. It does not, however, allow the natural 
      expression of task parallelism. Normal APL operations map well 
      to vector engines, but not to OS threads and concurrent programming. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Traditional solutions to task parallelism in APL bolted on
      concurrency constructs such as mutexes and
      guards, with APL underneath. This approach suffers from the
      same programmability problems that these same constructs have
      in any language, while additionally imposing a significant
      cost on language concision and productivity for
      domain experts. Such constructs serve domain experts little,
      even if the expert might otherwise benefit from a concurrent 
      paradigm. It also unnecessarily complicates the life of a 
      tuning expert.
      Deterministic parallelism somewhat relieves these
      issues by eliminating by construction some undesirable 
      non-determinism in parallel programs. The traditional expression 
      of these features, however, does not map any more nicely to 
      APL than mutexes, guards, or the like.
    </para>
    <para>
      Task parallelism in APL ought to satisfy two criteria: 
      it should feel like APL, and it should be easy to use safely.
      That is, these constructs should not destroy
      APL's concise expression, nor greatly burden domain experts to use.
      Co-dfns extends the basic dfns language to enable
      both non-deterministic and deterministic task parallelism
      without requiring any additional syntax, and introducing only
      two new primitives to the language.
    </para>
    <para>
      Firstly, a new literal <literal>⌾</literal> (target) represents the
      new datatype, a single assignment array. A single assignment
      array works like other arrays except that a slot in the array
      receives at most one value in its lifetime. The <literal>⌾</literal>
      value behaves like the empty vector literal <literal>⍬</literal>,
      except that its fill value is a single assignment slot.
      The reshape <literal>S⍴⌾</literal> builds
      a single assignment array of shape <varname>S</varname>, where 
      <varname>S</varname> gives the dimensions of the array. This
      array begins empty, and each slot may be assigned a value at most once. 
    </para>
    <programlisting>A←2 2⍴⌾  ⍝ SA matrix of shape 2 2
A[0;0]←1 ⍝ Assign 0 0 slot to 1
A[0;0]←5 ⍝ Error, multiple writes</programlisting>
    <para>
      Attempting to read a slot in a single assignment array blocks until 
      that slot receives a value. In this way, single assignment arrays 
      deliver IVars in a fashion that completing integrates them with 
      normal APL: they feel like any other normal array during use. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Co-dfns provides concurrent execution through an operator
      <literal>∥</literal>. The expression <literal>F∥</literal> is
      equivalent to the function <varname>F</varname> but when applied 
      returns immediately with a single assignment array whose values 
      will contain the results of executing F concurrently with the rest 
      of the program. Assuming <varname>F</varname> does not deadlock, 
      the array returned is equivalent to the array that would have been 
      returned by the function called without <literal>∥</literal> 
      assuming no error conditions.
    </para>
    <programlisting>pfib←{ ⍝ Parallel Fibonacci
  1=⍵:1
  2=⍵:1
  (pfib∥⍵-1)+(pfib∥⍵-2)
}</programlisting>
    <para>
      These two primitives suffice to deliver task parallel computation 
      in the dfns APL dialect. Single assignment arrays allow for 
      synchronization, while the parallel operator enables concurrency. 
      This approach requires no explicit control constructs or syntax.
      These primitives present an attractive alternative to
      traditional approaches because of the implicit and concise expression 
      of concurrency and synchronization. Moreover, by restricting all 
      inter-thread arrays (arrays touched by more than one thread) to single 
      assignment arrays, these constructs also exhibit determinism.
    </para>
  </section>
  <table frame="void">
    <title>APL Syntax Summary</title>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Expression</th>
        <th colspan="2">Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>f A</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">Apply <varname>f</varname> to <varname>A</varname>.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>A f B</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          Apply <varname>f</varname> to <varname>A</varname>
          and <varname>B</varname>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>V←Expr</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          Give <literal>Expr</literal> the name <varname>V</varname>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>A[B]</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          Extract array of same shape as <varname>B</varname> from 
          <varname>A</varname> by using each element in <varname>B</varname>
          as an index into <varname>A</varname>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>S1 ⋄ S2</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          Evaluate <literal>S1</literal> and then <literal>S2</literal>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><literal>{ ... }</literal></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          Function definition
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><varname>⍺</varname></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          The left formal argument in a function definition.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><varname>⍵</varname></td>
        <td colspan="2">
          The right formal argument in a function definition.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <section>
    <title>Implementation</title>
    <para>
      The Co-dfns compiler has a few explicit design goals:
    </para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Address problems in that prevent APL scaling to modern hardware
          and parallel systems.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Make it easy to embed the compiler into existing tools,
          namely the Dyalog interpreter, but also any other tools.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support additional tooling through clear, well defined interfaces
          and documentation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Produce standard compilation products that integrate with
          existing compiler toolchains and other languages.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support concurrency as a tool of thought for domain experts
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      As seen in the previous section benchmarking the Dyalog interpreter,
      memory management and locality play critical roles in the performance
      of the system. Indeed, these represent some of the most important obstacles
      to scalability of APL implementations.
      Furthermore, the existing systems, while taking advantage of vectorized
      operations on the CPU, do not as yet take good advantage of the GPU
      for SIMD operations in a way that preserves good cache behavior.
      Until version 14.0 (which incorporates some of the ideas presented here),
      Dyalog APL has no good story for task parallelism, and even with version
      14.0, it does not have a good story for fine grained parallelism/concurrency
      as a tool for domain experts and tuning experts to leverage seamlessly into
      existing dfns code.
    </para>
    <para>
      To address these issues, the compiler firstly leverages the existing work
      on traditional compilers by using the LLVM framework, which permits the
      compiler to ignore traditional compiler issues, such as procedure inlining,
      register allocation, and many other niceties. It also ensures that we have a
      neutral back-end which can produce code for both CPUs and GPUs. Work continues
      on doing auto-vectorization of code using polyhedral analyses within the
      LLVM community, which is encouraging. By using LLVM, the compiler is able
      to focus on the issues directly related to parallel scaling issues. It also
      gives the compiler the ability to generate traditional object files for free.
      These object files can then be used by the clang system to generate shared
      libraries or linked directly against other programs written in C or C++.
      As discussed later, Co-dfns functions map one to one to normal functions within
      a C or C++ function, and have a clear, well-documented signature for interfacing
      to them. This enables an easy integration of Co-dfns compiled code with other
      systems.
    </para>
    <para>
      Importantly, the Co-dfns compiler is itself written in dfns, with the
      intention of eventually self-hosting. This allows the compiler to exist
      directly in any Dyalog APL workspace, and can be used as just another
      evaluation or <quote>fixing</quote> function. Users of the regular
      Dyalog environment can easily compile modules that they have written as
      easily as loading the files from the file system.
    </para>
    <para>
      The compiler structure follows the NanoPass style, which builds a compiler
      in a functional, stateless manner by progressive application of small passes
      that accomplish small transformations to the AST. This makes it very easy to
      plug in additional passes anywhere along this process. The AST itself
      has a direct serialization to XML, permitting any language with XML support
      to handle and manipulate the AST of the compiler, feeding it back into
      the system whenever desired. Each of the interfaces from pass to pass and
      the associated invariants have documentation which clearly indicates the
      expectations of the pass.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the moment, the compiler has no conception of the GPU or the CPU.
      Instead, it expects the runtime to handle this. By swapping out the runtimes
      of the systems, you get code that runs on the GPU or code that runs on the
      CPU. However, further integration and support for these different platforms
      in the compiler itself would improve the performance of the system measurably.
    </para>
    <para>
      The current compiler does not yet implement all the Co-dfns language, but
      it does take advantage of one interesting feature of the language. Most
      interpreters for high-level languages, and indeed, most compilers, use
      some form of garbage collection. The Co-dfns language does not require
      garbage collection. Furthermore, it does not require closures, despite allowing
      for function values to thread through operators. This allows for almost all
      the benefits of higher order programming, but without the associated costs.
      It does result in some limitations of expressivity, but this trade-off seems
      worth it.
    </para>
    <para>
      In Co-dfns, a function may not escape its enclosing scope. Values, likewise,
      have stack or function lifetimes, rather than indefinite extent. Thus, each
      Co-dfns function corresponds to a regular LLVM function, which takes
      at least three array pointers, the result array and the right and left arrays.
      The function may not mutate the left or right arrays, but it should store
      the final result of the computation in the result array. All local variables
      receive stack allocation for their headers, an their data contents appear on
      the heap. Finally, to reference free variable inside of a function,
      each function receives zero or more frame pointers that point to the head of
      the frame for a containing lexical scope. This makes reference to free variables
      the same as referencing a local variable, except in a different frame.
    </para>
    <para>
      No benchmarks have been run to quantify the exact extent of the benefit of
      this stack closure strategy. At the very least, it makes it easier to
      inline code in Co-dfns without any great effort on the compiler's part.
      It also makes it much easier for Co-dfns functions to integrate into existing
      systems, as the calling conventions are the same.
    </para>
    <para>
      That Co-dfns is intended to be self hosted presents an important benchmark
      and implementation goal: to scale compilers to efficient implementation on
      the GPU. Passes in Co-dfns are written in such a way as to minimize the
      amount of serial or recursive operation, and prefer parallel and aggregate
      operations friendly to GPU execution.
    </para>
  </section>
  <figure>
    <title>Black Scholes Benchmark Code</title>
    <programlisting>r←0.02 ⋄ v←0.03 ⋄ p←÷(○2)*0.5

CNDP←{
  K←÷1+0.2316419×L←|⍵
  R←p×(*(L×L)÷¯2)×{coeff+.×⍵*1+⍳5}¨K
  (1 ¯1)[B]×((0 ¯1)[B←⍵≥0])+R
}

BlackScholes←{
  expRT←*(-r)×T ⋄ vsqrtT←v×T*0.5
  D1←((⍟S÷X)+(r+(v*2)÷2)×T)÷vsqrtT
  D2←D1-vsqrtT
  CD1←CNDP D1 ⋄ CD2←CNDP D2
  R←(S×CD1)-X×expRT×CD2
  R,[0.5]((X×expRT×1-CD2)-S×1-CD1)
}</programlisting>
  </figure>
  <section>
    <title>Evaluation</title>
    <para>
      The Co-dfns compiler does not yet support the entire language, and it 
      does not currently implement many of the intended optimizations designed 
      for it. This makes evaluation challenging, as most benchmarks leverage 
      a fairly wide array of language features and primitives. Notwithstanding
      these challenges, the Co-dfns compiler can compile the Espen Haug 
      Black Scholes calculation. 
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Blackscholes benchmark</title>
      <para>
        The black scholes formula estimates options pricing, and the 
        implementation of black scholes favors APL Interpreters to a fair 
        degree. Particularly, it requires very little code, and an APL 
        implementation contains very little structural control flow, 
        reducing the interpreter overhead. Moreover, the benchmark deals 
        mostly with scalar calculations over large arrays, for which 
        APL can implement specialized primitives that perform very well.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      The benchmark does a good job of measuring the performance of APL 
      on number crunching applications heavy with scalar computation. It 
      also benefits from good memory and cache locality as the size of 
      the data set increases. 
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Benchmarking Methodology</title>
      <para>
        To compare the Co-dfns compiler and Dyalog APL, the benchmarking 
        harness simulates as much as possible the intended use case of 
        the compiler. That is, execution of the compiled code should 
        occur as transparently as possible from within the Dyalog APL 
        system, and should not require excessive tooling. 
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      The current state of the compiler limits to some degree the level 
      of attainable integration. In particular, the benchmark was 
      compiled offline and linked together as a shared object, rather 
      than taking advantage of LLVM's MCJIT system. Additionally, a 
      custom wrapper function handled the conversion of interpreter 
      data structures to and from the compiler structures, calling out 
      to the shared object to perform the actual computation. This simulates 
      the work that the JIT would do, but it still forms an undesirable 
      manual step in the benchmarking process. 
      The compiled objects were compiled using clang 3.4 with O3 optimizations, 
      but no other explicit optimization settings. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Each version of the benchmark, one for the interpreter and one for the 
      compiler, used the same APL implementation of the black scholes, though 
      the code used for the compiler was cosmetically tweaked to work around 
      some limitations in the current implementation of the compiler. 
      Each version ran on each data set size three times, and the average 
      of these three computations was taken. Each run performed a collector 
      compaction before running the code. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The testing machine used an Intel Core i7-3610QM CPU @ 2.30Ghz with 
      16GB of RAM with Dyalog APL 14.0 Beta 3 on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 
      7.0 Beta. 
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Results</title>
      <para>
        See the figures for two versions of the same results, one on a 
        logarithmic scale and the other without any logarithmic adjustment. 
        The logarithmic scale demonstrates the performance characteristics 
        of the smaller sizes, while the linear scale demonstrates the 
        proportions of performance factors at large sizes better. 
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      Note that the interpreter outperforms the naive, partial implementation 
      of the compiler at low data sizes, but then begins to suffer performance 
      degredation as the size increases. The compiler begins to outperform 
      the interpreter, increasingly so as the sizes of the data grows. 
      The compiler outperforms the interpreter by 26% at the largest data set, 
      without performing any specific optimizations available to it. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The performance of the compiler at the low-end likely indicates the 
      inefficiency of the current approach to injecting and projecting data 
      to and from the compiled code, as this would most significantly influence 
      the results at the low-end. Moreover, the interpreters handling of locality 
      likely contributes to the failure to scale linearly as the data increases. 
      The compiler does a better job of this right now, but could undoubtedly 
      improve a great deal through the use of fusion optimizations. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <figure pgwide="1">
    <title>Black Scholes Benchmark Results</title>
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" width="3.5in" 
                   fileref="linear.svg" format="SVG" />
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" width="3.5in"
                   fileref="logarithmic.svg" format="SVG" />
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
  </figure>
  <section>
    <title>Related Work</title>
    <para>
      Froma theoretical standpoint, Lenore Mullin's dissertation on the
      Mathematics of Arrays provides a foundation upon which much of the
      compiler optimizations are based, in terms of reasoning about the shapes
      of arrays and their overall values. Heretofore, this work has not been
      incorporated into the compiler, but in the future it will serve as the
      basis for a number of planned compiler passes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Timothy Budd implemented an APL compiler for a traditional APL system
      that he describes in <quote>An APL Compiler</quote>. The work presents
      a unique and interesting approach to reducing computation on arrays
      by lazily executing computations. Budd's compiler delayed computation
      until the point at which the program requested the value. As in most
      traditional APL compilers, the language of the compiler does not match
      directly with the semantics of normal APL programs of the time. Budd's
      compiler also managed allocation without requiring a garbage collector.
    </para>
    <para>
      Bob Bernecky implemented the APEX compiler, which perhaps best represents
      the traditional APL compiler. It has useful passes, such as data flow
      analysis and static single assignment. Moreover, Bernecky details an
      approach at introducing parallelism into the compiler itself. While the
      APEX compiler is not self-hosting, the efforts to introduce a parallel
      expression of the compiler passes should inform the design of the Co-dfns
      passes and their design. The APEX compiler does suffer from a strong
      number of restrictions, some of which could evaporate given enough
      programmer effort. Both the APEX and Co-dfns compilers share some
      restrictions, such as not allowing the dynamic fixing of new functions
      at runtime. However, much more effort is made to ensure that existing
      dfns programs in Dyalog will run without modification in the Co-dfns compiler
      than the similar compatibility in the APEX compiler.
    </para>
    <para>
      Dyalog has provided a good deal of input into the Co-dfns compiler, and
      so it makes sense that the upcoming release of their interpreter begins
      to implement some of the ideas embedded into the Co-dfns compiler. This
      includes a facility for doing coarse-grained parallelism with futures,
      but does not include any ability to do more refined concurrent operations
      since the interpreter lacks single assignment arrays for synchronization;
      the system itself makes not guarantees when effects occur in parallel.
    </para>
    <para>
      A number of systems such as Manticore, ZPL, and Accelerate are able to
      provide interesting implementation strategies for array programming,
      each emphasizing different elements. They all take the overall approach
      of altering the language design in favor of making certain features
      prevalent. Accelerate, for instance, lifts rank to the type level,
      meaning that shapes are no longer first class entities. ZPL uses a
      more traditional language but enables predictable data layout for distributed
      computing. Manticore takes advantage of the language and implemenation to
      make heavy use of fusion and fision.
    </para>
    <para>
      Eric Holk's Harlan system takes a unique approach. Targeting the GPU
      explicitly, it tries to introduce traditional programming concepts as
      native concepts on the GPU, so that traditional programs can run reasonably
      on the GPU. This approach, instead of lifting array programming to the
      general-purpose sphere, pulls general-purpose language constructs such as
      ADTs into the GPU and array world through the use of region inference and
      a number of other transformations. It also uses the NanoPass style of
      compiler design and includes a macro system on top of it to reduce the
      number of core forms for the compiler to deal with.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Moving Forward</title>
    <para>
      The current version of the compiler does not yet implement all of the
      features of optimizations intended. The current development plan leads
      to a self-hosting compiler that will run on the GPU and CPU.
    </para>
    <para>
      The first optimization to integrate is scalar function fusion, which
      improves the basic locality issues of scalar primitives.
    </para>
    <para>
      The current compiler naively gives each named variable in
      a scope its own frame. However, it is possible to reuse array space
      for multiple variables that are not live at the same time. This has
      additional benefits on cache locality and allocation overhead.
      Furthermore, it is possible to push as much as possible to the result
      array, so that as little new allocation as possible is done in a
      given call frame, making tight loops even tighter. This will allow
      many regular data applications to operate without every doing any
      allocation outside of the first initial setup.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using shape analysis on the arrays, the compiler can determine ahead
      of time the size and shape of many arrays, and do this allocation well
      in advance of the computation. This in itself may not help, but these
      allocations may be lifted outside of a function, allowing a previous
      copying operation to occur as a mutation of an existing array instead.
      On benchmarks like the Graph500 this can save copying overhead in
      tight loops and make GPU performance much better.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order for the compiler to be truly useful, however, the rest of
      the dfns language must be implemented. This will allow a much greater
      range of benchmarks, and will allow real user testing and deployment.
    </para>
    <para>
      Looking far into the future, static assertions in the form of a
      dependent type system could provide for a great deal of information
      on which to make good compiler optimizations. This holds much potential,
      but remains a far reaching goal while the compiler remains in an
      incomplete state.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <para>
      Bob Bernecky provided excellent insight into the state of APL
      compilation. Dyalog, Ltd. has provided gracious funding for the
      development of this compiler. Ryan Newton and Andrew Lumsdaine 
      have greatly aided in directing this research. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <appendix>
    <title>Demo description</title>
    <para>
      Description of the demo of the tool.
    </para>
  </appendix>
  <appendix>
    <title>APL Primitives</title>
    <para>
      A simple cheat sheet for what all the APL primitives do.
    </para>
  </appendix>
</article>
