<variablelist xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Properties for Func. Expr. Canonical Sequence Analysis</title>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Opnd</term>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        What is the current function value without taking into consideration
        the current operator? This would be the left operand if there
        is an operator to deal with, and would be the function value
        if there is not. It does not include content in an unclosed
        parenthesized group. Possible values are:
        <symbol>ATOM</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>AMB</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>NONE</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>JOT</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>MON</symbol>
        , or
        <symbol>DYA</symbol>
        .
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Oper</term>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        What is the current operator we are dealing with? This will
        be nothing if we have not seen an operator, or the semantic
        equivalent value of the operator that is currently at the top
        of the parse tree. Possible values are:
        <symbol>NONE</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>DOT</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>COMP</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>POW</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>MON</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>DYA</symbol>
        . This property is for talking about what is outside of a currently
        opened parenthesis.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Axis</term>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Indicates whether a function can take an axis specification
        or not. It also indicates whether an axis specification has
        already been seen, and whether an expression for the axis specification
        has already been seen. Possible values are:
        <symbol>NO</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>YES</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>SEEN</symbol>
        , or
        <symbol>FILD</symbol>
        .
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Nest</term>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Determines whether a parenthesis has been seen, and what value
        was found in the nesting. Possible values are:
        <symbol>NONE</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>EMPTY</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>A</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>AA</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>M</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>MA</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>D</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>DA</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>O</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>OM</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>OD</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>COMM</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>COMP</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>EACH</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>POW</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>DOT</symbol>
        ,
        <symbol>RED</symbol>
        , or
        <symbol>SCN</symbol>
        .
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Target</term>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>Identifies whether or not we are currently in a targetable
      position where a variable may be assigned. This is a boolean
      value.</simpara>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
