<glosslist xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Tasks</title>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 1</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Identify architectural assets</title>
        <para>
          Identify and analyze architectural assets applicable to the 
          software, including existing domain models, reference 
          architectures, components, communication protocols, standards,
          and design strategies and conventions.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        Record the asset analysis in the <citetitle>Software 
        Architecture</citetitle> work product.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 2</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Define a strategy for the software architecture</title>
        <para>
          Define a strategy for the architecture based on the 
          <citetitle>Software Requirements</citetitle>, the 
          <citetitle>Function Specification</citetitle>, the analysis of the 
          architectural assets, and the requirements derived from higher level 
          system or subsystem design.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        Document the strategy in the <citetitle>Software 
        Architecture</citetitle>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 3</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Specify the top-level box structure of the software 
        architecture</title>
        <para>
          Decompose the history-based black box specification of required 
          external behavior defined in the <citetitle>Function 
          Specification</citetitle> into top-level, state-based state box and 
          procedure-based clear box forms based on the architecture strategy.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        For the state box, invent principal state elements and operations 
        required to achieve specified black box behavior.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the clear box, invent procedures for operations on state elements 
        required to achieve specified state box behavior. Within the clear 
        box, invent and connect principal software components, usually 
        defined as black boxes, whose subsequent state box decompositions 
        will encapsulate state at the next level.
      </para>
      <para>
        Continue the decomposition until the architecture is fully elaborated. 
      </para>
      <para>
        The completed software architecture represents hierarchies of box uses, 
        wherein every use of a box is represented explicitly in a hierarchy.
      </para>
      <para>
        Document the architecture in the <citetitle>Software 
        Architecture</citetitle> work product.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Task 4</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Analyze and validate the software architecture</title>
        <para>
          Perform simulations and analysis as necessary to ensure 
          that performance, reliability, usability, and other software requirements 
          can be met by the architecture.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>
        Document the analysis in the <citetitle>Software 
        Architecture</citetitle> work product.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glosslist>
