<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
    This chapter details the complete function specification of the Co-dfns
    compiler. The end result uses a black-box method of stimulus history inputs 
    and responses to model the entire behavior of the compiler. Specifying 
    a compiler completely is complex and not for the feint of heart. 
    Sequence-based enumeration forms the foundational core for this 
    specification, with a number of these enumerations defining the 
    abstract specification of the various components of the compiler. 
    The components in this chapter represent the abstract tasks that 
    a compiler like this much complete, and do not necessarily imply 
    any specific architectural design, though implementations will 
    likely want to stick with the overall decomposition of the compiler 
    as given in this specification.
  </para>
  <para>
    The entire behavior of the compiler is specified here, including 
    all of the features that are desirable from an user's point of 
    view but which may have very internal workings. That is, things 
    like optimizations and the like are also specified here, not just 
    semantics preserving transformations. After the abstract system 
    boundaries delineate the primary componenets of the system, 
    each component is specified with one or more sequence-based enumerations, 
    which are then converted into black-box specifications after 
    canonical sequence analysis. 
  </para>
  <para>
    All behavior here is dictated by the
    <citetitle>Software Requirements</citetitle>
    which in turn have the
    <citetitle>Programmer's Guide and Language Reference</citetitle>
    for Dyalog APL as an implicit dependency. Likewise, this specification
    assumes and relies on the language reference as an implicit part
    of this specification and will clarify behaviors not given complete
    treatment here. Complete treatment may not be granted here in the
    case that the behavior is adequately documented in the language reference.
  </para>
</section>
