<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Format and Notation</title>
  <simpara>
    Simplified, high-level structural graphs and markov chains
    describe the general system operation and usage models. The high-level
    models elide certain transitions in favor of simplicity.
    Some recursive stimuli, namely, the expression and function expression
    stimuli are too
    complicated to easily diagram, due in part to the handling of parentheses
    and brackets
    as well as other book keeping states. The high-level graphs corresponding
    to these
    stimuli in this document use a reduced state space intended to expose
    the important
    states for understanding the overall structure of the stimuli and its
    appearance in
    correct code productions. States that handling redundant nesting,
    parentheses, or
    states that are using only as <quote>error states</quote> do not appear
    in these
    diagrams. All models will have a corresponding matrix representation.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
    Each recursive stimuli states space and the top-level states will be
    given explicit short names
    to simplify their exposition throughout. These names are also chosen to
    reflect pneumonics
    that more accurately express their actual use, rather than the first
    canonical sequence
    in the enumeration that corresponds to the state. Arguably this is a
    less useful excercise,
    but it will be worth it if the diagrams are even a bit more intuitive.
  </simpara>
  <xi:include href="format_and_notation/short_names_toplevel.xml" />
  <xi:include href="format_and_notation/short_names_func.xml" />
  <xi:include href="format_and_notation/short_names_expr.xml" />
  <xi:include href="format_and_notation/short_names_funcexpr.xml" />
  <simpara>
    All high-level markov chains given here contain only a single
    merged transition from state to state, mergin any transitions that
    lead to the same target state from the same origin state. This allows for
    a simplified representation of Markov chains as matrices. All probabilities
    in the models are estimates and represent rough expected usage patterns
    that are not to be taken literally, but only serve to inform further
    refinements of these models during Usage Modeling and Test Planning.
  </simpara>
</section>
