<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>High-level Usage Models</title>
  <simpara>
    The following usage models describe the Top-level and Function recursive stimuli
    models, leaving the Expression and Function Expression models well under-modeled.
    This is because the function expressions and expressions both have a good number
    of states and are quite complicated. The Function and Top-level states give a good
    picture of the behavior of the system and are a good way of describing the system.
    For the Expression and Function Expression models, non-parenthesized expressions are
    modeled here, but these models elide parenthetical states.
    Even with these simpler models, only the non-error transitions are recorded for
    each state. This gives a concept of the non-error paths through the system, but
    does not allow for an adequate description of the precise usage behaviors.
    These models provide only the general idea of how correct usage of the system
    may proceed.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
    The tables indicating the transition probabilities from each edge are in percentages.
    A 0 value is actually a very small percentage, rather than a purely zero value.
    These transitions are given as an estimate on the most common use case of the
    Tweaking Tuner, who is likely to be dealing with mostly correct code. This models
    code as it is already commonly written and would be edited for performance
    purposes. Other use cases would likely have more errors in them, since the code
    would not be so well tested.
  </simpara>
  <figure>
    <title>High-level Markov Model of Top-Level</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.75in">
          <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/models/Top-Level_High-level_State_Graph.svg" />
        </imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/transition_probabilities/toplevel.xml" />
  <figure>
    <title>High-level Markov Model of Functions</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.75in">
          <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/models/Functions_High-level_State_Graph.svg" />
        </imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/transition_probabilities/functions.xml" />
  <figure>
    <title>High-level Markov Model of Expressions</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.75in">
          <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/models/Expression_High-level_State_Graph.svg" />
        </imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/transition_probabilities/expressions.xml" />
  <figure>
    <title>High-level Markov Model of Function Expressions</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.75in">
          <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/models/Function_Expression_High-level_State_Graph.svg" />
        </imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <xi:include href="high_level_usage_models/transition_probabilities/function_expressions.xml" />
</section>
