<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <info>
    <title>Co-Dfns Software Architecture</title>
  </info>
  <simpara>
    This document describes the high-level system architecture of the
    Co-Dfns compiler at the module and top levels. This includes the
    high-level design of passes and their box-based specifications,
    the programming approach used to develop each of the passes and
    the methodology of handling state-box specifications.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
    The methodology for handling the state-based specifications are
    different and differ from the practices found in normal
    box-structure methods. This is because the overal design favors a
    pure-functional approach, or one that is externally functional for
    any given level of abstraction. This necessitates no change in the
    clear or black box specifications, but requires a different
    approach for state-based structured specification and design. The
    <citetitle>Cleanroom Engineering Guide</citetitle> documents this
    new approach for those who wish to understand it in more detail as
    it is understood within the scope of this project.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
    After reading this document, the approach, design, and structure
    of the compiler should be evident, and it should be possible to
    navigate source files without difficulty or to understand the
    reasoning behind the creation of certain essential functions or
    how they fit together. The dependencies, orderings, and
    relationships between functions and elements should be clear, as
    should be the expectations and implied elements not clearly
    documented in the source code itself. Developers who wish to
    understand the source code should rely heavily on this document as
    the main document that guides the structure and implementation of
    the compiler.
  </simpara>
  <xi:include href="asset_analysis.xml" />
  <xi:include href="software_strategy.xml" />
  <xi:include href="top_level_structure.xml" />
  <xi:include href="runtime_design.xml" />
</chapter>
